Guide to the Julius Hartt Musical Foundation Inc. records ARCH161
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Julius Hartt Musical Foundation, Inc. records
1934-1998
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Julius Hartt Musical Foundation Inc.
Hartford Musical Foundation Inc.
ARCH161
2.92 Linear Feet (7 containers)
The collection consists primarily of board of trustee and committee minutes. It also contains records of Yehudi Menuhin's residency and Kennedy Center Honors Ceremony, as well as files on various significant people and events of which the Board may have been involved.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to all researchers.
Historical Note
In 1934, the Hartford Musical Foundation Inc. was founded by Julius Hartt, Moshe Paranov, Samuel Berkman, Stephen Langton, Helen Hubbard, Rose Lischner, Rubin Segal. In a November 1936 board meeting it was proposed that the Foundation consider changing their name, but no decision was made that year. On June 29, 1937 the amendment to the articles of association were filed to change the name to the Julius Hartt Musical Foundation, Inc. The board minutes of 1937 and 1938 are missing, but in 1939, the first bylaws of the Julius Hartt Musical Foundation, Inc. gave the original incorporators of the Hartford Musical Foundation life membership in the board of trustees.
The JHMF, Inc. board was the governing body of the school prior to the merger of Hartt, the Hartford Art School, and Hillyer College in 1957. Today the board functions in an advisory capacity and appoints several members to the board of regents.
Custodial History
These files were delivered to the archives in May of 2012 by the administrative offices of the Hartt School.
Scope and Contents
These materials consist primarily of the minutes of the Julius Hartt Musical Foundation Board of Trustees and its committees. The collection also contains some supplementary material which may have been used by the board.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series: I. Board of Trustees and Committees; II. Yehudi Menuhin; and III. People, Events, and Publications
Hartt College of Music; Hartt School; Hartt School. Community Division; Menuhin, Yehudi, 1916-1999; Paranov, Moshe, 1895-1994; Hartt, Julius; Julius Hartt School of Music
- Board of Trustees and Committees, 1934-1999
  Arrangement
  The files in this series are arranged in rough chronological order by its earliest date.
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1934-1999 (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3)
  - Bylaws, Merger, and Deincorporation, 1959-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Executive Committee, 1975-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3-11)
  - Budget Committee, 1977-1981 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - Facilities and Equipment Committee, 1977-1982 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Committee on Trustee Members, 1977-1983 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
  - Community Division Committee, 1977-1984 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
  - Community Affairs and Community Relations Committee, 1977-1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Educational Policy Committee, 1977-1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Development Committee, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 10, Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Committee on Special Programs and Projects, 1979-1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Allen Memorial Library Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Trustee and Hartt Faculty Library Committee, 1982-1988 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Board of Trustees, 1989-1998, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Yehudi Menuhin, 1984-1987; Bulk 1986 Dec - 1987 Feb
  Biographical / Historical
  Yehudi Menuhin was a world-renowned concert violinist. Menuhin had a brief residency at the Hartt School of the University in February 16-21, 1987. Prior to the Yehudi Menuhin residency, Menuhin received a Kennedy Center Lifetime Achievement Award at the Kennedy Center Honors Gala on December 7, 1986. Several Hartt students as well as the entire Hartt Symphony Orchestra were in attendance. It was Menuhin's request that Hartt students accompany his private violin student, Leland Chen, in a performance of two movements of Vivaldi's Four Seasons.
  These two events were significant honors for the Hartt School as the Hartt Symphony Orchestra was the first music school in the country to perform for the Kennedy Center Honors Gala and the first to obtain an educational residency from the world renowned violinist. CPTV made a television documentary, "Menuhin at Hartt" about his residency.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists primarily of materials between December 1986 and February 1987 which cover the proposal for the Menuhin Residency, as well as correspondence, planning documents, news clippings, and a concert program.
  - Menuhin Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Kennedy Center Honors Program, 1986 Nov-Dec (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Menuhin Observer Coverage, 1986 Nov - 1987 Mar (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Menuhin Proposal, 1986 Dec 17, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Menuhin Mailing, 1987 Jan (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Residency Sponsors, 1987 Jan (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Menuhin Concert Planning, 1987 Jan-Feb (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Menuhin Concert Admissions, 1987 Jan-Feb (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Menuhin Clippings, 1987 Feb (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Menuhin Recording, 1987 Oct (Box 7, Folder 2)
- People, Events, and Publications, 1960-1987
  Files are arranged in alphabetical order (files regarding people are filed by last name).
  - Samuel Berkman, 1966-1987, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Samuel Berkman Development, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Samuel Berkman Memorial, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Convocation with Jihan Sadat, 1983 May 31 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Alfred C. Fuller Music Center Dedication, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Alfred C. Fuller Memorial, 1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Handbook, 1960, undated (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
  - Donald Harris Correspondence with Ernest Bloch, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Donald Harris Correspondence with George Burns, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Donald Harris Correspondence with Elmer Nagy, 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Student Recitals, 1957; 1961 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Trustees, 1949-1980 (Box 7, Folder 16)